All right, we are going to talk about
conversion. So if you want to convert
from one um data type to another, you do
something called parsing. So let's say
we want to get an input from the user.
We want to ask how old they are. We can
say um that our age um and I'm going to
say age is a string because we know
everything that comes back from a prompt
is a string. So we'll say age string
equals prompt what is your age? And then
we'll put a semicolon. And then on the
next line, I'm going to alert the type
of age string. So this should tell me
what type of information I have in age
string. If we've done everything
correctly, we expect this to be a string
cuz we know everything that comes back
from a prompt is a string. So I'm going
to save this. I've got my live server
running already. So when I go over to my
website, I get a popup. It says, "What
is your age?" We'll enter 99. We'll hit
okay. And it says that is a string. So,
just like we expected, everything that
comes back from a prompt is a string.
So, what I'm going to do is I'm going to
add a new line in between these lines of
code. And so, right here, um, I'm going
to say let a oops, I apologize. Been
coding in Python too long. And they
don't use the keyword let, but let is
important to put in front. So, you'll
say let age string equal prompt. What is
your age? that will create a variable,
give it a name, and then assign the
result of the prompt to that variable.
I'm going to create a new variable here.
I'm going to say let age int equal
prompt
or sorry equal and then we're going to
convert this age string into an age
integer. The way we do that is we say
parse and then we use this parse int
function. So, we're going to hit tab and
then um I'm going to undo that real
quick so I can show you the little
IntelliSense hint. So, we're say parse
and then you'll notice that this parse
int has a purple cube. Anytime you see a
purple cube, that means it's a function,
which means you need to put parentheses
after it. We will talk about functions
in greater depth in the future, but just
as a rule of thumb, if it is this square
inside of brackets, you don't need
parenthesis. If it's a cube, you need
parenthesis. So, we're going to do this
parse int. It requires parenthesis. So,
we're going to put our opening
parenthesy. And then, if we pause, it'll
give us this hint that tells us what we
need to put inside of these parenthesis.
So, it says this thing converts a string
into a number. And the input it takes is
a string. So, do we have a string to
convert? We do. On line 17, we created a
variable called age string. We're going
to take that age string. We're going to
put it in here. and then it's going to
convert it into an integer. So I'm going
to type age string.
I'm going to put a semicolon and then
now on the next line I'm going to alert
type of age string. Now rather than we
already know age string is a string
because it came from a prompt. We want
to know the type of age integer. If this
says that it is a number, it means our
conversion has worked successfully.
So we're going to save that and come
over to our code. Says what is your age?
We'll say 99. We'll hit okay and it says
that is a number. So fantastic. We've
now converted from a string to a number
which means any of the methods that we
use to change how a number is uh being
stored in our system will be able to use
now with this variable called age
integer.
Now some of you may have been watching
and realized that that is a lot of lines
of code just to convert an input into a
number. We already knew we wanted age to
be a number. We've created now two
variables just to get age as a number
and you probably don't want to do that.
So let me show you how to put this on
one line. So we said let's create a
variable called age string and then
we're going to assign the value of that
variable meaning the thing it's going to
store is going to be whatever the user
entered here. We also know that this
parse int can take in a string. We know
that whatever the user types in comes
back as a string. So the way we can
simplify this onto one line is we can
take our prompt
and remove it. And where we had age
string, we can place our prompt. So
we're going to get a string. It's going
to take the result of that string, send
it to the parse int. It's going to parse
that into an integer and store it as age
int. So now we don't need this line of
code anymore.
And now that we only have one variable,
we can just call this variable age. So
we're going to call it age.
If we alert type of age, I'm just going
to prove to you that this is the exact
same thing. So we'll go over to our
website. We'll say what is our age? 99.
We'll hit okay. And it says is a number.
So it's successfully converting.
Um what I'm going to do is I'm going to
alert just age right now. And I'm going
to show you the difference between parse
int and parse float. So, if I save my
code and I come over to the website, it
says, "What is your age?" If I say 99.5
and said, "Okay, it just alerts 99." So,
it dropped the 0.5, which in some cases
is great. If um if you are intending to
only have a whole number, I guess that
works. But if you're rounding grade
points or something like that and you
were at a 99.9, you want your you want
it to round up to 100 and not down to
99. So, what we're going to do is we're
going to show you how to convert it from
a string into a number that has a
decimal place or a float. So, we're
going to come over here. All we do is we
change this from being parse int to
parse float. And now, if we save it and
we come back over, it says, what is your
age? We'll say 55.4.
And we'll hit okay. And the alert is
55.4.
If we come back over here and we alert
type of age and save and go back over to
our code, what is your age? 55.4.
Hit okay. And it says it's a number. So,
we've successfully converted into a
number that retains the decimal place.
So, if you want to keep the decimal
place, use parse float. If you want to
just have the whole number, then you can
just use parse int. And that concludes
this video. Thanks for watching.